Hi. This is Matt Baker. Today I’m
going to show the family tree of birds,
meaning how birds are currently classified
according to the latest research into their
evolutionary history. I’ll be starting with how
they evolved from dinosaurs and then how they
went in different directions from there,
leading to the various families, orders,
and other categories that they are sorted into
today. And the reason I am doing this is because
Today, on Kickstarter, we are launching our
Expanded Tree of Life project. Of the many
educational posters that we sell at UsefulCharts,
one of the most popular has always been our
Evolutionary Tree of Life chart, which we did
a major update of in 2024. Ever since then,
I’ve been wanting to go into certain parts of that
tree in greater detail—which is what this project
is all about. Basically, the goal is to create a
series of 4 posters, each of which will expand on
a different part of the tree of life. The first
one, Plants & Fungi, is already finished but in
order to complete the other three, we need your
help. The exact breakdown is yet to be determined,
but they are likely to be: Insects & Other
Invertebrates; Fish, Amphibians, and Reptiles;
and finally Bird & Mammals. Each chart will be
printed on thick, quality paper at an amazingly
high resolution so if you want be among
the first to receive one of these titles,
I encourage you to pre-order now. You can
choose to receive any one chart out of the four,
any two charts out of the four, or the full set.
You can also simply show your support by pledging
$1, which helps drive the Kickstarter algorithm.
We’ve got some fun stretch goals planned and will
have everything printed and mailed out by the
end of November, so whether you’re buying for
yourself or giving them as holiday gifts, I
encourage you to back the project right now.
You can do so by clicking the link
in the description or pinned comment
or by going to useful charts dot com
slash kickstarter. Also, take note:
What I'm using in this video is just a working
copy of what will eventually become a final
product. So if you see any mistakes or
feel like I missed something important,
do leave a comment because there’s
plenty of time for me to make changes.
Okay, let’s now dive into the family
tree of birds. As you probably know,
birds are literally living dinosaurs (which means
that they are also technically reptiles—although
they are generally classified separately as they
differ considerably from all other surviving
reptiles). When it comes to dinosaurs, they can
basically be divided into two main categories: the
now extinct Ornithischia (meaning bird-hipped; one
example being triceratops) and Saurischia (meaning
reptile-hipped). Ironically, birds actually
descend from the reptile-hipped dinosaurs,
which can be further divided into Theropods
(which once included the mighty T. Rex) and the
now extinct Sauropods (which included the largest
land animals ever, such as the arachiosaurus).
During the Age of Dinosaurs, there was a type of
theropod called the Paraves, the most well-known
of which is the now extinct Archaeopteryx. Well,
the Aves Class (which includes all modern birds)
also descends from and is still considered a
part the Paraves clayde. So we’re now at the
start of the Birds section, which is everything
shown in yellow, orange, or red. The word aves
is simply the Latin word for bird and from here,
things go in three different directions. There’s
the Palaeognathae, the Galloanserae, and the
Neoaves. The word “Palaeognathae” simply means
“old jaws” and was chosen because the birds
in this group are anatomically closer to the
extinct dinosaurs (especially in the beak and
sternum area) as compared to other modern birds.
They are also notable in that most of them
have lost the ability to fly, such as the
ostriches in Africa, rheas in South America,
emus in Australia, and kiwis in New Zealand.
The word Galloanserae is simply a combination
of Gallo (which is Latin for rooster) and
anserem (which is Latin for goose). Birds in this
clayde are known as fowl and belong to either the
waterfowl order (called Anseriformes, after the
word for goose) or land fowl (called Galliformes,
after the word for rooster). Aside
from quail (who have their own family),
most of the familiar types of land
fowl belong to the Phasianidae,
or pheasant family. In addition to pheasants,
this family also includes grouse, partridges,
turkeys, and of course, chickens (all of which are
types of birds commonly eaten by humans). However,
it also includes peafowl, which are
rarely eaten but instead admired for
their beautiful feathers. Take note that the
word peacock only refers to the male members
of the species and when referring to a female,
the word is actually pea-hen. When it comes to
waterfowl, most are in the [uh-NAHT-uh-dee]
Anatidea, or duck family, which of course,
includes ducks (such as the famous mallard)
as well as swans, geese, and Canada geese.
But the vast majority of bird species (about
95%) belong to the Neoaves (which literally
means “new birds”), hence the switch of color to
orange here. Now, just two 2 years ago, in 2024,
the way that Neo-a-ves were classified was
changed based on a major genetic study. It
is now thought that they can be divided into
four main claydes: the Mirandornithes (which
is basically just flamingoes and grebes, the
Columbaves (named after the Latin word for dove),
Elementaves (after the word “element”)
and Telluraves (which means “land birds”).
Let’s start with the Columbaves, most of which
belong to the Columbiformes Order and Columbidae
Family (the main exception being the cuckoo birds
and road runners (which have their own order and
family). So, in this family, we of course get
doves, such as collared doves and turtle doves as
well as mourning doves. But we also get pigeons,
such as the domestic (or feral) pigeon that is
found in city parks and which descends from the
wild rock dove. Now, prior to the 20th century,
a different pigeon (known as the passenger pigeon)
was actually far more common in North America.
However, due to overhunting and deforestation,
they went from a population of 4 billion to being
extinct in less than 100 years, with the last
passenger pigeon dying in 1914. But don’t get
the passenger pigeon confused with the carrier
(or homing) pigeon, the kind that delivers
messages. They are actually just specially trained
domestic pigeons and are still around to this day.
Also in this family is perhaps the most
famous extinct animal of all time—the dodo,
which lived on the remote island of Mauritius,
in the Indian Ocean. Because it had no natural
predators and lots of food, it evolved to the
point where it lost its ability to fly. Thus,
when humans showed up with dogs and other animals,
they quickly went extinct, probably by 1690.
Okay, let’s now look at the Elementaves,
so named because they can be found in many
different environments or elements—such at sea,
on land, or along the shore. All shorebirds belong
to the Charadriiformes Order, which includes the
plover family, the sandpiper family, and the gull
family (which also includes terns and skimmers).
Now true seabirds (which are placed in a clayde
called Aque-ornithes) differ from shorebirds in
that they spend most of their time actually in
the water (rather than just alongside it). So,
here we find loons (aka "stupid Canadian wolf
birds”) which btw are NOT ducks, even though they
look like ducks. We also get storks, cormorants,
and penguins (yet another type of bird that has
lost its ability to fly) as well as all the birds
in the Pelican Order, many of which have evolved
away from the sea and into freshwater areas,
such as certain herons, and [ai-buses] ibises.
Now, one other type of bird that you might have
assumed we would have come across in either the
seabird or shorebird category would be cranes. But
they’re almost exclusively freshwater birds (found
mainly in marshes)—which is why they’re placed
separately over here. A lot of people confuse
cranes with herons so one way to tell them apart
is that cranes fly with their necks stretched out
whereas herons fly with their necks in an S shape.
One last order that is unexpectedly included
among the Elementaves is the Apodiformes,
which includes swifts and hummingbirds.
What sets them apart from other birds is
their extremely short legs. You see, pod meets
foot so a-pod literally means “without feet”.
Okay, we’re now ready to tackle the final (and
by far the largest) type of Neo-a-ves: the
Telluraves, or core land birds. But before I do
so I want to point out that most of the individual
bird images on this chart were taken from the
citizen science website iNaturalist (but only from
observations with photos marked public domain).
In case you're unfamiliar with iNaturalist, it
has an app that can be used to identify and make
a record of nature observations (not just birds
but also plants, mushrooms, insects, et cetera).
This video is not sponsored by iNaturalist but
I wanted to bring it up in case there are any
other inatters out there who’d like to help by
either contributing photos or suggesting things to
include. You can find me on iNaturalist under the
username matt hyphen b so feel free to message
me there or tag me in specific observations.
Okay, let's now take a look at the Telluraves.
Since 2012, this clayde has been further divided
into two groups, based on a split that occurred
around the time of the KT extinction event.
There's the Afroaves, which evolved on
what became Africa; and the Australaves,
which evolved on what became South
America and Australia. In Afro-a-ves,
we get the two main raptor (or birds of prey)
orders: Accipiteriformes and Strigiformes. In
[ak-sip-uh-tree FOR-meez] Accipiteriformes,
we get the osprey family and the hawk family
(which includes not only hawks but also
eagles and buzzards). In Strigiformes,
we get all the various type of owls. Barn owls
get their own family called Tytonidae whereas
most other owls (such as horned owls, snowy owls,
and wood owls) are found in the Strigidae family.
Take note that barred owls (not to be confused
with barn owls) are a type of wood owl. Also
in the Afroaves category is the scavenger
Cathartiformes Order (which includes turkey
vultures and condors) as well as kingfishers
and woodpeckers. Woodpeckers are placed in the
Picidae family and here, I’ve chosen to show the
four most common types of woodpeckers in the US.
Moving over to the Australaves, we find the
falcons—the other major type of raptor. It used to
be that hawks, eagles and falcons were all placed
in one big order but now, due to genetic studies,
we know that falcons evolved from a totally
different branch. In fact, they are more closely
related to parrots than they are to hawks. All
parrots can be found in the Psittaciformes Order,
where cockatoos get their own family and where
macaws, grey parrots, and Amazon parrots are all
placed together in the main parrot family. That
family (the Psittacidae) should not be confused
with this similarly named Psittaculidae family,
which is where budgies and lovebirds are placed.
Okay, we now come to the most important
order found within the Austral-a-ves,
if not the entire Av-es Class: the
Passeriformes—which is where we find
about 60% of all bird species. This order is so
large that I decided to give them their own color:
red. Now the name Passeriformes is based on
the Latin word for sparrow, which is Passer,
and indeed, all birds in this order kind of look
like sparrows. But more importantly, they are
all “perching” birds, which means that they can
easily grab hold of and perch on branches. This
is because their feet evolved to have three long
toes in the front and one long toe in the back,
which makes wrapping them around a branch
really easy. Now, most Passerines (which
is what we call birds in this order) are also
songbirds but a few are not, so let me point
them out first. We’ve got the New Zealand wrens
in this very small suborder as well as the New
World flycatchers in the Tyranni suborder, which
is why they’re also called tyrant flycatchers.
Okay, let’s now talk about songbirds, which are
all birds belonging to the Passeri Suborder.
Songbirds (also known as Oscines) differ from
all other birds in that they have several
extra muscles in their windpipes and these
allow them to produce more complex sounds,
which they use to pass on information and
to attract mates. The Passeri suborder can
be divided into two infraorders: the Passerides
infraorder (which includes most songbirds) and
the Corvides infraorder, which is where we find
corvids. Now, corvids are special because they
are the smartest birds on the planet, with an
intelligence level roughly equivalent to that
of a 7 year old child. While they cannot
mimic human speech as well as parrots can,
they are able to solve more complex puzzles,
build tools out of multiple parts, and remember
human faces over many years. Included in
this family are jackdaws, magpies, jays,
rooks, ravens, and of course, crows. In most of
North America, there is just one crow species:
Corvus brachyrhynchos (which literally
means “short-nosed crow). However,
in Europe, there are at least two: the all-black
carrion crow and the black-and-grey hooded crow.
Right. Let’s now move order to Passerides
infraorder, which we’re once again going to
divide up, this time into three parvorders.
First there’s theSylviidae parvorder,
which is where we find the Paridae (or “tit”
family). There’s no need to giggle—the word
simply comes from an old Scandinavian word
that means “small”. And indeed, this family
does include some of the smallest songbirds
(such as the familiar chickadee). However,
take note that bushtits (which are even smaller)
are placed in their own family. Also closely
related are the Old World warblers, larks, and
swallows. Now, I should pause for a minute here
and explain the terms Old World and New World.
Old World refers to Europe, Africa, and Asia;
whereas New World refers to the Americas. These
are obviously terms based on colonization and are
therefore problematic but unfortunately they
are still the main terms used in taxonomy.
The important thing to understand is that there
are often two different versions of many types
of birds (such as warblers). Basically,
when the Europeans came to the Americas,
they saw some birds that looked to them like the
warblers they had back home—and therefore they
called them “warblers” (even though we now know
that they’re not actually closely related). We’re
going to see this come up again with sparrows,
robins, finches, and a bunch of other birds).
Next up is the Muscicapida parvorder, named after
the Muscicapidae family, which literally means
“fly-catching” family. Here we find the European
robin, which is a type of flycatcher. But also in
this parvorder are the thrushes, which are not
flycatchers and instead belong to the Turdidae
family. This is where we find the red-breasted
American robin, as well as the Eurasian blackbird,
plus all the various species of bluebirds. Also
in Muscicapida are mockingbids, wrens, nuthatches,
kinglets, and starlings. Starlings are notable in
that they are sometimes flock together to create
large murmurations. However, in North America,
they are often considered pests because they don’t
belong here and can end up outcompeting native
birds. You see, originally, starlings only lived
in Eurasia but then, in the late 1800s, a small
number of them were released in New York’s Central
Park because, well, it seemed like a nice idea at
the time. Unfortunately, there are now about 100
million of them in North America, and like I say,
they often outcompete native birds so nowadays,
starlings are mostly a lesson in what not
to do when it comes to wildlife management.
The final parvorder here is Passerida,
which is where we find the Passeridae
(or Old World sparrow) family, which is the
type of bird that the entire Passeriformes
Order is named after. The sparrow shown here
is a House Sparrow, which, like the Starling,
was originally just a Eurasian species
but was then introduced to North America,
where it has since become invasive. However, also
in the same parvorder is the or finch family,
which includes both Old World and New World
species. Finches are different from other
songbirds in that they tend to have short, stout
beaks that are really good at breaking nuts. So,
in this family, we get the chaeff-inch, this
goldfinch (both from Europe) as well as the
house finch and this goldfinch (both from
North America). Then there’s the canary,
which was originally from Europe but has since
been domesticated and sold all over the world
as pets. In the US, they were also infamously
sent into coal mines to detect carbon dioxide.
The final set of birds were going to look at all
come from the Americas and are known as New World
Nine-Primaried Oscines. “Nine-Primaried”
refers to fact that they have only 9 main
feathers on their wings (as opposed to
most other birds, which usually have 10,
just like we have 10 fingers). So, first of all,
there’s the Cardinal family, which of course
includes the Northern Cardinal (probably the most
easily recognized bird in North America). However,
it also includes certain grosbeaks, buntings, and
tanagers (although most “true” tanagers belong
to there own family, here). Another important
Nine-Primaried family is the Icteridae family,
which is where you’ll find grackles,
orioles (such as the Baltimore Oriole),
and the New World blackbirds. There’s also the New
World warbler family (which I pointed out earlier)
and then finally, the Passerellidae, or (New
World sparrow) family. Like I mentioned earlier,
these sparrows aren’t as closely related to the
Old World sparrows as you might think, even though
they are both called “sparrows”. European settlers
simply named them sparrows because they looked a
lot like the house sparrow that they were used
to back home. So, in contrast to the European
house sparrow, sparrows that are native to North
America include crowned sparrows, song sparrows
as well as towhees and juncos (even though those
last two aren’t directly named as being sparrows).
Okay, so that was a look at the family tree of
birds. I’d love to hear in the comments which
bird species are the most common in your
own backyard. Here in Vancouver, Canada,
at my (and my wife’s) birdfeeders, we mostly
get house finches, goldfinches, chickadees,
song sparrows, juncos, Northern flickers, Anna’s
hummingbirds, and of course American crows).
Now, before you go, be sure to check out our
Kickstarter campaign (which will be live for
the entire month of August) and if you can,
please back the project by either signing
up to pre-order posters or by simply pledging one
dollar. If you don’t have the funds to contribute,
you can also help by sending the link to
friends or by sharing it on social media.
Thanks for your support and thanks for watching.